# SAAD AHMED

# Curriculum Vitae

Technology Square Research Building School of Interactive Computing, Atlanta, GA ⑤ (+1) 7738238029 ☐ sahmed@gatech.edu ☐ https://www.saadahmedch.com ☐ Github inLinkedin

### Research Interest

I work towards building a sustainable future for computing by providing system support for battery-less embedded devices. My research revolves around developing compiler and run-time techniques to enable long-running and computationally complex applications on embedded devices powered by harvested energy. I apply my work to mobile health as well as to enable novices and hobbyists in designing applications for energy harvesting devices. My research interests also include wearable computing, low-power wireless sensors, and computer architecture.

I have published in 8 A\*/A conferences (according to CORE rankings) such as Ubi-Comp(2x), SenSys, IPSN, EuroSys, EWSN, LCTES (2x), and top computing journal such a TECS and TCPS. My work has been covered by top media outlets such as Scientific American, TechCrunch, Gizmodo, Forbes and the ACM Tech News.

## Education

2016–2020 **PhD, Computer Science**, *LUMS School of Science and Engineering*, Pakistan.

Advisor: Dr. Muhammad Hamad Alizai

Dissertation: Fast and Energy-efficient Intermittent Computing

2014–2016 **MS, Computer Science**, *LUMS School of Science and Engineering*, Pakistan.

Advisor: Dr. Asim Karim

2009–2013 **BS, Computer Science**, *National University of Computer and Emerging Sciences*, Pakistan.

Advisor: Dr. Fakhar-ul-Islam Lodhi Project: PL/SQL to MySQL Conversion

Bronze Medal: Among top 2% in a batch of 200 students

## Selected Five Publications

#### EuroSys'23 Efficient and Safe I/O Operations for Intermittent Systems.

Eren Yildiz, <u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Bashima Islam, Josiah Hester, Kasim Sinan Yildirim To appear in European Conference on Computer Systems (EuroSys'23)

Acceptance rate = 14%

#### SenSys'22 **Protean: Adaptive Battery-free Computing Platform.**

Abu Bakar, Rishabh Goel, Jasper de Winkel, Jason Huang, <u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Bashima Islam, Przemysław Pawełczak, Kasım Sinan Yıldırım, Josiah Hester

InACM Conference on Embedded Networked Sensor Systems (SenSys'22)

**ACM SIGMOBILE Research highlight** 

### UbiComp'22 Battery-free MakeCode: Accessible Programming for Intermittent Computing.

Chris Kraemer, Amy Guo, Saad Ahmed, Josiah Hester

ACM Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp'22)

Published in PACM IMWUT, Volume 5, Issue 4

**Covered by ACM Tech News** 

#### UbiComp'22 FaceBit: Smart Facemask Platform.

Alexander Curtiss, Blaine Rothrock, Abu Bakar, Nivedita Arora, Jason Huang, Zachary Englehardt, Aaron-Patrick Empedrado, Chixiang Wang, <u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Yang Zhang, Nabil Alshurafa, Josiah Hester ACM Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp'22)

Published in PACM IMWUT, Volume 5, Issue 4

**Fast Company's Innovation by Design Award Finalist** 

Covered by Top media outlets including Scientific American, TechCrunch, Forbes, Gizmodo and many more.

## EWSN'20 Intermittent Computing with Dynamic Voltage and Frequency Scaling.

<u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Qurat-u-Ain, Junaid Haroon Siddiqui, Luca Mottola, Muhammad Hamad Alizai International Conference on Embedded Wireless Systems and Networks (EWSN'20)

T Best Paper Nominee

# ACM TCPS ASHRAY: Enhancing Water-usage Comfort in Developing Regions using Data-driven IoT Retrofits.

Samar Abbas, Ahmed Ehsan, <u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Sheraz Ali Khan, Tariq Muhammad Jadoon, Muhammad Hamad Alizai

ACM Transactions on Cyber-Physical Systems (ACM TCPS)

# Academic Achievements & Recognitions

- 2023 Nomination for the College of Computing Postdoctoral Researcher Award
- 2022 SuperSensor got selected for the ACM SIGMOBILE Research Highlight
- 2022 FaceBit was the Fast Company's Innovation by Design Award Finalist
- 2021 Selection for the prestigious Alexandar Von Humboldt postdoctoral fellowship, Germany.
- 2020 D<sup>2</sup>VFS nominated for **Best Paper Award** nominated at EWSN
- 2017 First position in Intermittent Computing Hackathon at IDEA League Doctoral School
- 2013 **Bronze Medal**, Faculty of Computing, NUCES, Pakistan
- 2010-12 **Dean's Honor List**, Faculty of Computing, NUCES, Pakistan
  - 2013 Final Year Project among top 10%, Faculty of Computing, NUCES
  - 2010 Merit Based Selection for visiting UK's & EU's Top Universities, Govt. Of Punjab, Pakistan
- 2009-13 National Talent Scholarship, Govt. Of Punjab, Pakistan
  - 2009 Academic Roll of Honour, Govt. College University Lahore, Pakistan
  - 2009 **Gold Medal**, Higher Secondary School Exam, Pakistan

# Research Impact

**8** peer-reviewed conference papers (all of them are A or A\* conferences as per CORE 2018 Conference Ranking)

# **Professional Experience**

Georgia Institute of Technology, USA

Oct 2022 - **Postdoctoral Scholar** 

Present Mentor: Dr. Josiah Hester.

Northwestern University, USA

Dec 2020 - Postdoctoral Scholar

Sep 2022 Mentor: Dr. Josiah Hester.

Techlogix Inc., Pakistan

May 2013 - **Software Engineer**.

Nov 2014

## Research Experience

LUMS School of Science and Engineering, Pakistan

May 2020 - Research Associate

Nov 2020 Advisor: Dr. Muhammad Hamad Alizai.

May 2016 - Graduate Research Assistant

Nov 2020 Advisor: Dr. Muhammad Hamad Alizai.

RWTH Aachen, Germany

July 2016, Visiting Researcher

Aug 2017 Host: Dr. Klause Wehrle.

LUMS School of Science and Engineering, Pakistan

Jan 2016 - Research Assistant

Aug 2016 Advisor: Dr. Muhammad Hamad Alizai.

# Community Service

**Peer Review** 

Feb. 2023 Ad Hoc Networks

Oct. 2022	Journal of Systems Architecture
March. 2021	Ad Hoc Networks
Oct. 2020	IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing
July 2020	ACM Transactions on Sensor Networks
Oct. 2019	International Journal of Computer and Telecommunications Networking
Sept. 2019	IEEE International Conference on Parallel and Distributed Systems (ICPADS)
	Undergraduate Research
July 2022	Judge for the undergraduate research expo, Northwestern University
	Talks
Nov-2020	Fast and Energy-efficient Intermittent Computing, University of Southampton, UK
Nov-2020	Fast and Energy-efficient Intermittent Computing, KTH Royal Institute of Technology, Stockholm, Sweden
Feb-2020	Intermittent Computing with Dynamic Voltage and Frequency Scaling, EWSN, Lyon, France
June-2019	Differential Checkpointing for Intermittent Programs, LCTES, Phoenix AZ, USA
June-2019	Finding the Missing Joules of Transiently-powered Computers, LCTES, Phoenix AZ, USA
Aug-2016	Incremental Checkpoints for Interruptible Computations, RWTH Aachen, Aachen, Germany
	Fellowships & Grants
2021	Alexander Von Humboldt Research Fellowship (Selection), Germany
2020	National Data Center Travel Grant to attend EWSN, LUMS
2019	Student Travel Grant worth to attend LCTES, LUMS
2018	CPS Week Travel Grant to attend IPSN, CPS Week
2017	Travel Grant to attend Doctoral Colloquium at RWTH Aachen, DAAD
2016	Travel Grant to attend Doctoral Colloquium at RWTH Aachen, DAAD
	Publications

In Preparation

P2 **Batteryless Health Sensing powered by Intra-body Power Transfer.**Saad Ahmed, Eren Yildiz, Bashima Islam, Kasim Sinan Yildirim, Josiah Hester

#### P1 Data Cache for Intermittent Computing Systems with Non-Volatile Main Memory.

Vito Kortbeek, Sourav Mohapatra, Saad Ahmed, Przemysław Pawełczak

## In Conference Proceedings

#### **C8** Efficient and Safe I/O Operations for Intermittent Systems.

Eren Yildiz, <u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Bashima Islam, Josiah Hester, Kasim Sinan Yildirim To appear in European Conference on Computer Systems (EuroSys'23)

**Acceptance rate = 14%** 

#### **C7** Protean: Adaptive Battery-free Computing Platform.

Abu Bakar, Rishabh Goel, Jasper de Winkel, Jason Huang, <u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Bashima Islam, Przemysław Pawełczak, Kasım Sinan Yıldırım, Josiah Hester

InACM Conference on Embedded Networked Sensor Systems (SenSys'22)

**ACM SIGMOBILE Research highlight** 

#### **C6** Battery-free MakeCode: Accessible Programming for Intermittent Computing.

Chris Kraemer, Amy Guo, <u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Josiah Hester ACM Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp'22) Published in PACM IMWUT, Volume 5, Issue 4

**Covered by ACM Tech News** 

#### C5 FaceBit: Smart Facemask Platform.

Alexander Curtiss, Blaine Rothrock, Abu Bakar, Nivedita Arora, Jason Huang, Zachary Englehardt, Aaron-Patrick Empedrado, Chixiang Wang, <u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Yang Zhang, Nabil Alshurafa, Josiah Hester ACM Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp'22)

Published in PACM IMWUT, Volume 5, Issue 4

**Fast Company's Innovation by Design Award Finalist** 

Covered by Top media outlets including Scientific American, TechCrunch, Forbes, Gizmodo and many more.

#### C4 No-frills Water Comfort for Developing Regions.

Samar Abbas, Ahmed Ehsan, <u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Sheraz Ali Khan, Tariq Muhammad Jadoon, Muhammad Hamad Alizai

International Conference on Information Processing in Sensor Networks (IPSN'20)

#### C3 Intermittent Computing with Dynamic Voltage and Frequency Scaling.

<u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Qurat-u-Ain, Junaid Haroon Siddiqui, Luca Mottola, Muhammad Hamad Alizai International Conference on Embedded Wireless Systems and Networks (EWSN'20)

T Best Paper Nominee

# C2 The betrayal of constant power× time: Finding the missing joules of transiently-powered computers.

<u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Abu Bakar, Naveed Anwar Bhatti, Muhammad Hamad Alizai, Junaid Haroon Siddiqui, Luca Mottola

Proceedings of the 20th ACM SIGPLAN/SIGBED International Conference on Languages, Compilers, and Tools for Embedded Systems (LCTES'19)

### C1 Efficient intermittent computing with differential checkpointing.

<u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Naveed Anwar Bhatti, Muhammad Hamad Alizai, Junaid Haroon Siddiqui, Luca Mottola Proceedings of the 20th ACM SIGPLAN/SIGBED International Conference on Languages, Compilers, and Tools for Embedded Systems (LCTES'19)

#### **Journal Articles**

# J3 ASHRAY: Enhancing Water-usage Comfort in Developing Regions using Data-driven IoT Retrofits.

Samar Abbas, Ahmed Ehsan, <u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Sheraz Ali Khan, Tariq Muhammad Jadoon, Muhammad Hamad Alizai

ACM Transactions on Cyber-Physical Systems (TCPS)

#### J2 Fast and Energy-efficient State Checkpointing for Intermittent Computing.

<u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Naveed Anwar Bhatti, Muhammad Hamad Alizai, Junaid Haroon Siddiqui, Luca Mottola ACM Transactions on Embedded Computing Systems (TECS)

#### J1 Demystifying Energy Consumption Dynamics in Transiently-powered Computers.

<u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Muhammad Nawaz, Abu Bakar, Naveed Anwar Bhatti, Muhammad Hamad Alizai, Junaid Haroon Siddiqui, Luca Mottola

ACM Transactions on Embedded Computing Systems (TECS)

Workshops, Posters & Demos

#### W3 Towards smaller checkpoints for better intermittent computing.

<u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Muhammad Hamad Alizai, Junaid Haroon Siddiqui, Naveed Anwar Bhatti, Luca Mottola 17th ACM/IEEE International Conference on Information Processing in Sensor Networks (IPSN'18)

#### W2 Incremental Checkpointing Techniques for Transiently Powered Computers.

Saad Ahmed

Doctoral School on Transiently Powered Computing-Collocated with SenSys'17

#### W1 Incremental checkpointing for interruptible computations.

<u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Muhammad Hamad Alizai, Junaid Haroon Siddiqui, Naveed Anwar Bhatti, Luca Mottola Proceedings of the 14th ACM Conference on Embedded Network Sensor Systems (SenSys'16)

# Teaching Experience

Spring, 2022: **Internet-of-things**, *Co-Instructor*, Northwestern University.

Fall, 2020: Introduction to Internet of Things, Co-Instructor, LUMS.

Fall, 2018: Internet of Things, Teaching Assistant, LUMS.

Fall, 2014: **Operating Systems**, *Teaching Assistant*, NUCES.

Spring, 2014: **Operating Systems**, *Lab Instructor*, NUCES.

**Operating Systems**, *Teaching Assistant*, NUCES.

Fall, 2013: Operating Systems, Teaching Assistant, NUCES.

Fall, 2013: **Operating Systems**, *Teaching Assistant*, NUCES.

**Operating Systems**, Lab Instructor, NUCES.

# Student Mentorship

2022-2023	<b>Eren Yildiz</b> , <i>Kamoamoa's Visiting Student</i> , Ege University Turkey.
2019-2020	<b>Qurat-ul-Ain</b> , <i>MS-Thesis</i> , LUMS.
2018-2019	<b>Muhamamd Nawaz</b> , Research Assistant, LUMS, now Software Engineer-SIEMENS.
2017-2018	Abubakar, Research Assistant, LUMS, now PhD student-GT.
2016-2017	<b>Hassan Ali Khan</b> , <i>MS-Thesis</i> , LUMS, now PhD student in NC State University.
2016-2017	Ans Fida, UG, LUMS, Senior MTS-SalesForce.
2016-2017	<b>Kamran Khalil</b> , <i>UG</i> , LUMS, Ph.D. Purdue University -> SDE Amazon AWS.
2016-2017	Natasha Khan, MS-Thesis, LUMS, now Software Engineer-CERN.

### Referees

#### Dr. Muhammad Hamad Alizai

Assistant Professor,

Department of Computer Science

LUMS, Pakistan

⋈ hamad.alizai@lums.edu.pk

#### Dr. Luca Mottola

Associate Professor,
Dipartimento di Elettronica,
Politecnico di Milano, Italy

☑ luca.mottola@polimi.it

#### **Dr. Kasim Sinan**

#### Dr. Junaid Haroon Siddiqui

Associate Professor,
Department of Computer Science
LUMS, Pakistan

☑ junaid.siddiqui@lums.edu.pk

#### Dr. Bashima Islam

Assistant Professor,
School of Science and Engineering
WPI

☑ bislam@wpi.edu

#### **Josiah Hester**

Assistant Professor,
School of Interactive Computing
Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, USA

ignity josiah@gatech.edu

Last Updated: February 15, 2023